[
    {
        "question": "Radiocarbon is produced in the atmosphere as a result of",
        "a": "collision between fast neutrons and nitrogen nuclei present in the atmosphere",
        "b": "action of ultraviolet light from the sun on atmospheric oxygen",
        "c": "action of solar radiations particularly cosmic rays on carbon dioxide present in the atmosphere",
        "d": "lightning discharge in atmosphere",
        "answer": "collision between fast neutrons and nitrogen nuclei present in the atmosphere"
    },
    {
        "question": "It is easier to roll a stone up a sloping road than to lift it vertical upwards because",
        "a": "work done in rolling is more than in lifting",
        "b": "work done in lifting the stone is equal to rolling it",
        "c": "work done in both is same but the rate of doing work is less in rolling",
        "d": "work done in rolling a stone is less than in lifting it",
        "answer": "work done in rolling a stone is less than in lifting it"
    },
    {
        "question": "The absorption of ink by blotting paper involves",
        "a": "viscosity of ink",
        "b": "capillary action phenomenon",
        "c": "diffusion of ink through the blotting",
        "d": "siphon action",
        "answer": "capillary action phenomenon"
    },
    {
        "question": "Siphon will fail to work if",
        "a": "the densities of the liquid in the two vessels are equal",
        "b": "the level of the liquid in the two vessels are at the same height",
        "c": "both its limbs are of unequal length",
        "d": "the temperature of the liquids in the two vessels are the same",
        "answer": "the level of the liquid in the two vessels are at the same height"
    },
    {
        "question": "Large transformers, when used for some time, become very hot and are cooled by circulating oil. The heating of the transformer is due to",
        "a": "the heating effect of current alone",
        "b": "hysteresis loss alone",
        "c": "both the heating effect of current and hysteresis loss",
        "d": "intense sunlight at noon",
        "answer": "both the heating effect of current and hysteresis loss"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nuclear sizes are expressed in a unit named",
        "a": "Fermi",
        "b": "angstrom",
        "c": "newton",
        "d": "tesla",
        "answer": "Fermi"
    },
    {
        "question": "Light year is a unit of",
        "a": "time",
        "b": "distance",
        "c": "light",
        "d": "intensity of light",
        "answer": "distance"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mirage is due to",
        "a": "unequal heating of different parts of the atmosphere",
        "b": "magnetic disturbances in the atmosphere",
        "c": "depletion of ozone layer in the atmosphere",
        "d": "equal heating of different parts of the atmosphere",
        "answer": "unequal heating of different parts of the atmosphere"
    },
    {
        "question": "Light from the Sun reaches us in nearly",
        "a": "2 minutes",
        "b": "4 minutes",
        "c": "8 minutes",
        "d": "16 minutes",
        "answer": "8 minutes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stars appears to move from east to west because",
        "a": "all stars move from east to west",
        "b": "the earth rotates from west to east",
        "c": "the earth rotates from east to west",
        "d": "the background of the stars moves from west to east",
        "answer": "the earth rotates from west to east"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pa(Pascal) is the unit for",
        "a": "thrust",
        "b": "pressure",
        "c": "frequency",
        "d": "conductivity",
        "answer": "pressure"
    },
    {
        "question": "Metals are good conductors of electricity because",
        "a": "they contain free electrons",
        "b": "the atoms are lightly packed",
        "c": "they have high melting point",
        "d": "All of the above",
        "answer": "they contain free electrons"
    },
    {
        "question": "Let a thin capillary tube be replaced with another tube of insufficient length then, we find water",
        "a": "will overflow",
        "b": "will not rise",
        "c": "depressed",
        "d": "change its meniscus",
        "answer": "will not rise"
    },
    {
        "question": "Out of the following pairs, choose the pair in which the physical quantities do not have identical dimension?",
        "a": "Pressure and Young's modules",
        "b": "Planck's constant and Angular momentum",
        "c": "Impulse and moment of force",
        "d": "Force and rate of change of linear momentum",
        "answer": "Impulse and moment of force"
    },
    {
        "question": "If two bodies of different masses, initially at rest, are acted upon by the same force for the same time, then the both bodies acquire the same",
        "a": "velocity",
        "b": "momentum",
        "c": "acceleration",
        "d": "kinetic energy",
        "answer": "momentum"
    },
    {
        "question": "Pick out the scalar quantity",
        "a": "force",
        "b": "pressure",
        "c": "velocity",
        "d": "acceleration",
        "answer": "pressure"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rectifiers are used to convert",
        "a": "Direct current to Alternating current",
        "b": "Alternating current to Direct current",
        "c": "high voltage to low voltage",
        "d": "low voltage to high voltage",
        "answer": "Alternating current to Direct current"
    },
    {
        "question": "out of the following, which is not emitted by radioactive substance?",
        "a": "Electrons",
        "b": "Electromagnetic radiations",
        "c": "Alpha particles",
        "d": "Neutrons",
        "answer": "Neutrons"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sound waves in air are",
        "a": "transverse",
        "b": "longitudinal",
        "c": "electromagnetic",
        "d": "polarised",
        "answer": "longitudinal"
    },
    {
        "question": "Magnetism at the centre of a bar magnet is",
        "a": "minimum",
        "b": "maximum",
        "c": "zero",
        "d": "minimum or maximum",
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "question": "Find the maximum velocity for the overturn of a car moving on a circular track of radius 100 m. The co-efficient of friction between the road and tyre is 0.2",
        "a": "0.14 m\/s",
        "b": "140 m\/s",
        "c": "1.4 km\/s",
        "d": "14 m\/s",
        "answer": "14 m\/s"
    },
    {
        "question": "Of the following properties of a wave, the one that is independent of the other is its",
        "a": "amplitude",
        "b": "velocity",
        "c": "wavelength",
        "d": "frequency",
        "answer": "amplitude"
    },
    {
        "question": "Lux is the SI unit of",
        "a": "intensity of illumination",
        "b": "luminous efficiency",
        "c": "luminous flux",
        "d": "luminous intensity",
        "answer": "intensity of illumination"
    },
    {
        "question": "On a rainy day, small oil films on water show brilliant colours. This is due to",
        "a": "dispersion",
        "b": "interference",
        "c": "diffraction",
        "d": "polarization",
        "answer": "interference"
    },
    {
        "question": "Point A is at a lower electrical potential than point B. An electron between them on the line joining them will",
        "a": "move towards A",
        "b": "move towards B",
        "c": "move at right angles to the line joining A and B",
        "d": "remain at rest",
        "answer": "move towards B"
    },
    {
        "question": "Materials for rain-proof coats and tents owe their water-proof properties to",
        "a": "surface tension",
        "b": "viscosity",
        "c": "specific gravity",
        "d": "elasticity",
        "answer": "surface tension"
    },
    {
        "question": "RADAR is used for",
        "a": "locating submerged submarines",
        "b": "receiving a signals in a radio receiver",
        "c": "locating geostationary satellites",
        "d": "detecting and locating the position of objects such as aeroplanes",
        "answer": "detecting and locating the position of objects such as aeroplanes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sound of frequency below 20 Hz is called",
        "a": "audio sounds",
        "b": "infrasonic",
        "c": "ultrasonic",
        "d": "supersonics",
        "answer": "infrasonic"
    },
    {
        "question": "On a clean glass plate a drop of water spreads to form a thin layer whereas a drop of mercury remains almost spherical because",
        "a": "mercury is a metal",
        "b": "density of mercury is greater than that of water",
        "c": "cohesion of mercury is greater than its adhesion with glass",
        "d": "cohesion of water is greater than its adhesion with glass",
        "answer": "cohesion of mercury is greater than its adhesion with glass"
    },
    {
        "question": "Suitable impurities are added to a semiconductor depending on its use. This is done in order to",
        "a": "increase its life",
        "b": "enable it to withstand higher voltages",
        "c": "increase its electrical conductivity",
        "d": "increase its electrical resistivity",
        "answer": "increase its electrical conductivity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Moment of inertia is",
        "a": "vector",
        "b": "scalar",
        "c": "phasor",
        "d": "tensor",
        "answer": "tensor"
    },
    {
        "question": "Of the following natural phenomena, tell which one known in Sanskrit as 'deer's thirst'?",
        "a": "Rainbow",
        "b": "Earthshine",
        "c": "Halo",
        "d": "Mirage",
        "answer": "Mirage"
    },
    {
        "question": "Inside an aeroplane, flying at a high altitude,",
        "a": "the pressure is the same as that outside",
        "b": "normal atmospheric pressure is maintained by the use of air pumps",
        "c": "the pressure inside is less than the pressure outside",
        "d": "normal humidity and partial vacuum are maintained",
        "answer": "normal atmospheric pressure is maintained by the use of air pumps"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sound travels with a different speed in media. In what order does the velocity of sound increase in these media?",
        "a": "Water, iron and air",
        "b": "Iron, air and water",
        "c": "Air, water and iron",
        "d": "Iron, water and air",
        "answer": "Air, water and iron"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sound travels at the fastest speed in",
        "a": "steel",
        "b": "water",
        "c": "air",
        "d": "vacuum",
        "answer": "steel"
    },
    {
        "question": "oil raise up the wick in a lamp. The principle involves",
        "a": "the diffusion of oil through the wick",
        "b": "the liquid state of oil",
        "c": "capillary action phenomenon",
        "d": "volatility of oil",
        "answer": "capillary action phenomenon"
    },
    {
        "question": "Superconductors are substances which",
        "a": "conduct electricity at low temperature",
        "b": "offer high resistance to the flow of current",
        "c": "offer no resistance to the flow of electricity",
        "d": "conduct electricity at high temperatures",
        "answer": "offer no resistance to the flow of electricity"
    },
    {
        "question": "Light travels at the fastest speed in",
        "a": "glass",
        "b": "water",
        "c": "hydrogen",
        "d": "vacuum",
        "answer": "vacuum"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sound produced at a point is heard by a person after 5 second, while the same sound is heard by another person after 6 seconds. If the speed of sound is 300 m\/s, what could be the maximum and minimum distances between the two persons?",
        "a": "1.8 km, 0.15 km",
        "b": "2.2 km, 0.20 km",
        "c": "2.8 km, 0.25 km",
        "d": "3.3 km, 0.30 km",
        "answer": "3.3 km, 0.30 km"
    },
    {
        "question": "Intensity of sound at a point is ____ its distance from the source.",
        "a": "directly proportional to",
        "b": "inversely proportional to",
        "c": "directly proportional to square of",
        "d": "inversely proportional to square of",
        "answer": "inversely proportional to square of"
    },
    {
        "question": "Radio telescopes are better than optical telescopes because",
        "a": "they can detect faint galaxies which no optical telescope can",
        "b": "they can work even in cloudy conditions",
        "c": "they can work during the day and night",
        "d": "All of the above",
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "question": "Light Emitting Diodes (LED) is used in fancy electronic devices such as toys emit",
        "a": "X-rays",
        "b": "ultraviolet light",
        "c": "visible light",
        "d": "radio waves",
        "answer": "visible light"
    },
    {
        "question": "Out of the following pairs, which one does not have identical dimension?",
        "a": "Moment of inertia and moment of a force",
        "b": "Work and Torque",
        "c": "Angular momentum and Planck's constant",
        "d": "Impulse and Momentum",
        "answer": "Moment of inertia and moment of a force"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mercury is commonly used as a thermometric fluid rather than water because",
        "a": "specific heat of mercury is less than water",
        "b": "specific heat of mercury is more than water",
        "c": "mercury has greater visibility than water",
        "d": "density of mercury is more than the water",
        "answer": "mercury has greater visibility than water"
    },
    {
        "question": "Optical fibre works on the",
        "a": "principle of refraction",
        "b": "total internal reflection",
        "c": "scattering",
        "d": "interference",
        "answer": "total internal reflection"
    },
    {
        "question": "Light from the star, Alpha Centauri, which is nearest to the earth after the sun, reaches the earth in",
        "a": "4.2 seconds",
        "b": "42 seconds",
        "c": "4.2 years",
        "d": "42 years",
        "answer": "4.2 years"
    },
    {
        "question": "Supersonic plane fly with the speed",
        "a": "less than the speed of sound",
        "b": "of sound",
        "c": "greater than the speed of sound",
        "d": "of light",
        "answer": "greater than the speed of sound"
    },
    {
        "question": "Mach number is used in connection with the speed of",
        "a": "sound",
        "b": "aircraft",
        "c": "spacecraft",
        "d": "ships",
        "answer": "aircraft"
    },
    {
        "question": "On a stationary sail boat, air is blown from a fan attached to the boat. The boat",
        "a": "moves in opposite direction in which the air is blown",
        "b": "does not move",
        "c": "moves in the same direction in which air blows",
        "d": "spins around",
        "answer": "does not move"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rainbow is due to",
        "a": "absorption of sunlight in minute water droplets",
        "b": "diffusion of sunlight through water droplets",
        "c": "ionisation of water deposits",
        "d": "refraction and reflection of sunlight by water droplets",
        "answer": "refraction and reflection of sunlight by water droplets"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stars which appear single to the naked eye but are double when seen through a telescope are",
        "a": "novas and supernovas",
        "b": "binaries",
        "c": "asteroids",
        "d": "quasars",
        "answer": "binaries"
    },
    {
        "question": "Solar eclipse will take place when",
        "a": "the sun is between the moon and the earth",
        "b": "the earth is between the moon and the sun",
        "c": "the moon is between the sun and the earth",
        "d": "the moon does not lie on the line joining the sun and the earth",
        "answer": "the moon is between the sun and the earth"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sir C.V. Raman was awarded Nobel Prize for his work connected with which of the following phenomenon of radiation?",
        "a": "Scattering",
        "b": "Diffraction",
        "c": "Interference",
        "d": "Polarization",
        "answer": "Scattering"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which of the following industries is mica as a raw material?",
        "a": "Cement",
        "b": "Glass and Pottery",
        "c": "Iron and Steel",
        "d": "Electrical",
        "answer": "Electrical"
    },
    {
        "question": "Radiocarbon dating technique is used to estimate the age of",
        "a": "rocks",
        "b": "monuments",
        "c": "soil",
        "d": "fossils",
        "answer": "fossils"
    },
    {
        "question": "Identify the vector quantity from the following",
        "a": "Heat",
        "b": "Angular momentum",
        "c": "Time",
        "d": "Work",
        "answer": "Angular momentum"
    },
    {
        "question": "Large astronomical telescopes always use as objective",
        "a": "lens",
        "b": "mirror",
        "c": "combinations of lenses",
        "d": "None of the above",
        "answer": "combinations of lenses"
    },
    {
        "question": "One should not connect a number of electrical appliances to the same power socket because",
        "a": "this can damage the appliances due to overloading",
        "b": "this can damage the domestic wiring due to overloading",
        "c": "this can damage the electrical meter",
        "d": "the appliance will not get full voltage",
        "answer": "this can damage the domestic wiring due to overloading"
    },
    {
        "question": "Natural radioactivity was discovered by",
        "a": "Marie Curie",
        "b": "Ernest Rutherfor",
        "c": "Henri Becquerel",
        "d": "Enrico Fermi",
        "answer": "Henri Becquerel"
    },
    {
        "question": "One nanometer is equal to",
        "a": "10^-6m",
        "b": "10^-8m",
        "c": "10^-9m",
        "d": "10^-5m",
        "answer": "10^-9m"
    },
    {
        "question": "Minimum number of unequal vectors which can give zero resultant are",
        "a": "two",
        "b": "three",
        "c": "more than four",
        "d": "four",
        "answer": "three"
    },
    {
        "question": "Intensity of sound has",
        "a": "an object existence",
        "b": "a subject existence",
        "c": "no existence",
        "d": "both subjective and objective existence",
        "answer": "an object existence"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rain is falling vertically downwards. To a man running east-wards, the rain will appear to be coming from",
        "a": "east",
        "b": "west",
        "c": "northeast",
        "d": "southeast",
        "answer": "east"
    },
    {
        "question": "An aeroplane is flying horizontally with a velocity of 600 km\/h and at a height of 1960 m. When it is vertically at a point A on the ground a bomb is released from it. The bomb strikes the ground at point B. The distance AB is",
        "a": "1200 m",
        "b": "0.33 km",
        "c": "3.33 km",
        "d": "33 km",
        "answer": "3.33 km"
    }
]